This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
For Software Engineering Radio, this is
Robert Blumen. Today, I have with me
Alex Boten. Alex is a senior staff
software engineer at Lightstep. Prior to
that, he was at Cisco. He's contributed
to open source projects in the telemetry
area
including the OpenTelemetry project.
He's the author of the book Cloud Native
Observability with OpenTelemetry.
And that will be the subject of our
conversation today.
Alex, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio.
Hello. Thank you for having me. It's
great to be here.
Would you like to add anything about
your background that I didn't mention?
I think you captured most of it. You
know, I've been contributing to
OpenTelemetry for a little bit over 3
years. I've worked on various components
of the project as well as the
specification, and I'm currently a
maintainer on the OpenTelemetry
Collector. Great. Now, on Software
Engineering Radio, we have covered quite
a lot of telemetry-related issues
including
logging in episode 220,
high cardinality monitoring, which was
429, Prometheus,
distributed tracing,
and episode 455, which was called
Software Telemetry. So,
listeners can definitely listen to some
of those in our back catalog to get more
general information.
We'll be focusing more in this
conversation about what OpenTelemetry
brings to the table that we have not
already covered. Let's start out with in
the telemetry space,
where could you situate OpenTelemetry?
What is it similar to? What is it
different? What does it solve?
That's a great question. So, I think
the problem that OpenTelemetry aims to
solve, and we've already seen it happen
in the industry today, is it changes how
application developers instrument their
application, how telemetry is generated,
and how it's collected and then
transmitted across systems. And if I
were to think of, you know, what it's
similar to, the first thing that comes
to mind are the projects that really
caused it to emerge, which are
OpenCensus and OpenTracing, which are
two other open source projects that were
formed a little bit earlier. I think it
it started in maybe 2017, 2016, to
provide a standard around producing
distributed tracing, and also OpenCensus
also addressed a little bit around
metrics and log collection. What was
going on in the telemetry area prior to
those projects that created the need for
them, and what did they do? Yeah, so I
think, you know, if you think of
telemetry as a domain in in software,
it's been around for a really long time,
right? Like people as as early as, you
know, the earliest of computer
scientists wanted to know what their
computers were doing.
And, you know, earlier in the days of
having a single machine, it was it was
fairly easy to print some log statements
and look at what your machine was doing.
But as the industry grew, as the
Internet of Things picked up, as
systems became larger and larger to
address the the increasing demand, I
think systems became inherently more
complex, and we've seen an evolution of
what software telemetry really really
became. So, if you think of, you know,
earlier we were able to log data on a
single system, as people had to deploy
multiple systems, you know, a need for
centralized logging came along so that
you can aggregate and do aggregate
searches on logs.
And that became really costly, and then
we saw an increased in folks wanting to
capture more meaningful metrics from
their systems, where they could create
dashboards and and do queries, whereas
it was cheaper than going through and
analyzing log data.
And I think the thing that I've seen
happen in the last 20 years is every
time there was a new maybe paradigm
around the type of telemetry that
systems should emit, there has been a
chance for innovation to take place,
which
is great to see, but if you're an end
user who's just trying to get telemetry
out of a system, out of an application,
it's a really frustrating process to
have to go and reinstrument your code
every few months or every few years, you
know, depending on what the the flavor
of the day is. And I think what
OpenCensus and OpenTracing and
OpenTelemetry try to capture is
addressing the the pain that users have
when it comes to instrumenting their
code. What is the relationship of
OpenTelemetry to other systems out there
such as
Zipkin, Jaeger, Graylog, Prometheus? So,
the relationship that OpenTelemetry has
with with the Zipkins, the Jaegers, and
the Prometheuses of the world is really
around providing interoperability
between those systems. So, you know, an
application developer would instrument
their code using OpenTelemetry,
and then they can emit that telemetry
data to whatever back-end systems they
want. So, you know, if you wanted to
continue using Jaeger, you could
definitely do that with an application
that's instrumented with OpenTelemetry.
The other thing that OpenTelemetry tries
to do is it tries to provide a
translation layer so that folks that are
maybe today emitting data to Zipkin or
to Jaeger or to Prometheus can deploy a
collector within their environments and
then translate the data from a specific
format of those other systems into the
OpenTelemetry format so that they can
then emit the data to whatever back-end
they choose by simply updating the
configuration on on their collector
without having to go back to their
applications to maybe you know, legacy
systems that nobody wants to modify
anymore, and still be able to send their
data to different destinations. Is
OpenTelemetry then an interoperability
standard,
a system, or both? It's really the
standard to instrument your applications
and to provide the interop-
interoperability between the different
systems. There's no, you know,
OpenTelemetry doesn't offer a back-end.
There's no log database or metrics
database that OpenTelemetry provides.
Maybe at some point in the future that
that will happen. You know, we're
certainly seeing people that are
supporting the OpenTelemetry format
starting to provide those back-end
options for folks that are emitting only
OpenTelemetry data, but that's not
something the project is interested in
in solving at this point. It's really
about, you know, the instrumentation
piece and the collection and
transmission of the data. In reading
about this, I came across discussion of
a protocol called OTLP.
Explain what that is.
So, the OpenTelemetry protocol is a
protocol that's generated from protobuf
definitions every implementation of
OpenTelemetry supports. Its aim is to
provide high-performance data
transmission in a in a format that's
standardized across all the
implementations. It's also supported by
the OpenTelemetry Collector.
And what it really means is, you know,
so this this format supports all the
different signals that OpenTelemetry
supports, so log, traces, metrics, and
maybe down the road events and
profiling, which, you know, is currently
being developed in the project.
And the idea is if you support the
OpenTelemetry protocol, this is the
protocol that you would use to either
transmit the data, or if you're a vendor
or if you're a back-end provider, you
would use that protocol to receive the
data. And it's actually been really good
to see, you know, even projects like
Prometheus starting to support the OTLP
protocol for for transmitting data.
So, let me summarize what we have so far
and tell me if I've understood. If I'm
building an application, I could
instrument it in a way that's
compatible with the standard. I might
not even know where my logs or metrics
are going to end up, and then whoever
uses my system, which maybe people in
the same organization, or maybe I'm
shipping an open source project which
has many users,
they can then plug in their back-end of
choice, and
they are not necessarily tied to any
decisions I made about how I think the
telemetry will be collected. It creates
the ability of users to plug and play
between the applications and the
back-ends. Is that more or less correct?
Yeah, that that's exactly right. I think
it really decouples the instrumentation
piece, which, you know, historically has
been the most expensive aspect of of
organization gaining observability
within in their systems,
from the decision of where am I going to
send that data. And the nice thing about
this is that it really frees the end
users from from the idea of vendor
lock-in, which I think a lot of us who
have worked in in systems for a long
time always found it to be difficult,
you know, the conversation of trying to
maybe try out a new a new vendor if you
wanted to, you know, test some new
feature they wanted to have or whatever.
Usually would mean that you would have
to go back and reinstrument your code.
Whereas now with OpenTelemetry, if
you've instrumented your application,
hopefully this is the last time you have
to worry about instrumenting application
because you can just point that data to
different back-ends. A little while ago,
you did mention the collector, and we
will be spending some time on that. But
I want to understand what are the
possible configurations of the system.
What I think we're talking about now is
if the code is instrumented with the
OpenTelemetry standard, that it could
talk directly to back-ends. The other
option being you have a collector in
between them. Are those the two main
configurations?
Yeah, that's right. It's also possible
to configure your instrumented
application to send data to backends
directly. If you wanted to choose to
send the data to Jaeger, I think most
implementations that support
OpenTelemetry officially have a Jaeger
exporter, for example. So, there there
are options if you wanted to send data
from your application to your backend,
but ideally you would send the data in
in that you can you know configure using
an an OpenTelemetry collector later down
down the line.
Let's come back to collector in a bit,
but I want to talk about
instrumentation.
Often if I want to talk to a certain
backend, I need to use a different
library
to emit the telemetry.
How does that change with OpenTelemetry?
Yeah, so with the OpenTelemetry standard
you you have two aspects of the
instrumentation. So, there's the
OpenTelemetry API, which is really what
most developers would interact with.
There's a very limited amount of surface
area that the API covers. You know, for
example, for tracing the API's
essentially you can start a span and you
can you know finish a span
and get a tracer. That's that's roughly
the the surface area that's trying to be
covered there. And the idea we want to
push forward with with our limited APIs
to just reduce the cognitive load that
users would have to to take on to adopt
OpenTelemetry.
The other piece of the instrumentation
that folks will have to interact with is
the SDK, which really allows end users
to configure how the telemetry is
produced and where it's sent to.
If you're thinking about this in the
context of you know how is it different
from a particular backend and and its
instrumentation, the the difference is
with OpenTelemetry you you would only
ever use the OpenTelemetry API
and configure the SDK to send data to
the backend of choice, but the API that
you would use for instrumenting the code
wouldn't be any different depending on
which backend you send it to. And
there's that clear separation between
the API and the SDK that allows you to
to really only instrument with that
minimal interface
and worry about the details of how and
where that data is sent using the SDK
configuration, which in in my book I
refer to as you know telemetry
pipelines. In that
that discussion you mentioned
tracing. I've seen a lot of logging
systems, you can log whatever you want
and then it puts the
burden on a collector to pick up the
logs and format them.
And then metrics, you may have to use a
library.
If I'm adopting OpenTelemetry, how does
it handle logs and metrics?
Yeah, so for metrics there is an API
that calls out specific instruments. So,
OpenTelemetry has a list of I believe
it's six instruments currently that it
supports to more or less have the same
functionality as like the Prometheus the
Prometheus library. And I think a lot of
those instruments were developed in
collaboration with both the OpenMetrics
and the Prometheus communities to ensure
that
you know, we're compatible with with
those folks.
So, for the logging library, that's a
little bit different in OpenTelemetry or
at least it was at the time of writing
this the my book, which was written in
2021 mostly.
The idea behind logging and
OpenTelemetry was we already were aware
there were so many different APIs for
logging in each language. You know, each
language has like a dozen logging APIs
and we we didn't necessarily want to
create a new logging API that people
would have to adopt. And so, the idea
was to really hook into those existing
APIs.
It's been an interesting transition that
I think in the past maybe in the past
six or eight months or so, there's been
almost a an ask for an an API and an SDK
in the logging signal as well. That's
still currently in in development. So,
you know, stay tuned for what's going to
happen there. In what languages are the
OpenTelemetry
SDKs available? Yeah, so there's
currently 11 officially supported
languages.
I'm probably going to forget some of
them, but there's definitely one in C++
in Go in Rust in Python, Ruby, PHP,
Java, JavaScript. All those languages
are covered officially by OpenTelemetry.
And what what this means is that the
implementations were reviewed by someone
on the technical committee and the
implementation themselves live within
the OpenTelemetry organization in GitHub
and you know has the same process. We
have maintainers and approvers for each
one of those languages.
There's a couple of additional
implementations that aren't officially
supported yet, but that's really you
know just because there hasn't been
enough contributors to it yet. I think
there's one in Lua and maybe Julia is
the other one.
I've found when instrumenting code I
often spend a lot of time doing things
like writing a message that a certain
method has been called and here the
parameters.
Very boilerplate steps.
I understand that OpenTelemetry can to
some extent automate that. How does that
work?
Yeah, so there is you know one of the
very first OTEPs the OpenTelemetry
enhancement proposals that was created
in the early stages of the project was
to to support auto instrumentation out
of the box.
So, it
the effort of auto instrumentation in
different languages is at different
different stages. So, I know the the
Java and the Python auto instrumentation
efforts are are a little bit further
along. I think dot net is coming along
nicely and I think JavaScript is as
well.
But the idea behind auto instrumentation
with OpenTelemetry
is very similar to what we've seen in in
other efforts before where
it really it ties instrumentation to
existing third-party open source library
or third-party libraries, right? And the
idea being for example, if you're using
the Python SDK, I'm using that as an
example because I spent a decent amount
of time writing some code there. If
you're using the Python SDK and you
wanted to use for example, the like the
Python Redis library,
well, you could use the instrumentation
library that's provided by
OpenTelemetry, which allows you to call
to this library, which monkey patches
the the Redis library that it then makes
a call to, but you know, in that
intermediate step it acts as a middle
layer that instruments the calls to the
the library that you'd be making. So, if
you were calling you know, connect for
example, it would call connect on the
instrumentation library, start span,
maybe record some kind of metric about
the operation,
make the call to the Redis library and
then on the return it would end the span
and you know, produce some telemetry
there with some semantic convention
attributes.
Explain the term monkey patching.
So, monkey patching is when a library
intercepts a a call and replaces a call
with itself instead of the original
original call. So, in in the case of the
Redis example I was using,
the Redis instrumentation library
intercepts the call to connect to Redis
and then it replaces it with its own
connect call, which does the
instrumentation as well.
This I could see being very useful in
that if you have got a library and
something's going wrong inside of the
library, you don't know where,
then the previous option has been that I
need to get the source code of the
library and if I want logging I would
have to go and
insert log statements or insert metrics
or whatever type of telemetry I'm trying
to capture into someone else's source
code and rebuild it. So, does this
enable you to get visibility of what is
happening inside third-party libraries
that
you've downloaded with your package
manager and you're not interested in
modifying the code.
Right. I think that's a that's a key
benefit of it is that you're finally
able to
see what these libraries are doing. Or
maybe you know, maybe you're not
familiar with the code or you're not
really sure of the path through the code
and you're able to see you know, all of
the library calls that are instrumented
underneath your original call of your
application, which you know, a lot of
the time you'll find problems there, but
it's really hard to identify them
because you don't you don't necessarily
know what's happening without reading
the source code underneath at all. Have
you used some of those languages in the
11? I'm aware that every language is
different as far as what access it gives
you to intercept things at runtime or
maybe generate
bytecode and inject it into the library.
I would think that the ability to do
this is going to differ considerably
based on the language and maybe C++
being rather unfriendly to that. Do you
expect to achieve a parity with all the
languages in the extent that you can
offer this feature or will it always
work better on some than others?
That's a great question. I think ideally
I imagine that instrumentation libraries
are a a temporary fix. I I really
believe that what everybody is hoping
for within the community and we've seen
some you know, open source projects
already reach out and and start
instrumenting their applications. We're
really hoping that
these libraries will use the
OpenTelemetry API to instrument
themselves
and remove the need for these
instrumentation library altogether. For
example, if you know, if an HTTP server
framework were to instrument
its calls to its endpoints using
OpenTelemetry, the end user wouldn't
even need this instrumentation library
and you know, we could achieve parity
across all the languages because each
one of those libraries would just use
this the standard rather than
you know, relying on either bytecode
manipulation or monkey patching, which
you know, I
it works for what it is, but it's it's
not always the greatest option, you
know, with monkey patching, maybe the
underlying libraries call changes
parameters,
and you know, you have to keep track of
of those changes within those
instrumentation libraries, and so that
that always poses a challenge. But
ideally, like I said, those libraries
would will go away as the project
continues to gain traction across
industry. And we've already seen, you
know, I I think there was a few Python
open source projects that reached out. I
know the spring folks in Java had a had
a project to instrument using open
telemetry, you know, Envoy and a few
other proxies have also started using
open telemetry, so it's it's definitely
I think instrumentation that were great
for the short-term, but in the long-term
it would be ideal if if things were
instrumented themselves.
That would be great, but there are
always going to be some older libraries
that may be not under as active
development where
there's not really anyone around to
modify them. Then you always have this
to fall back on in those cases.
I wouldn't see it going away.
Right. Ideally, it would the norm would
become instrument your, you know,
libraries with with open telemetry, and
you know, for those libraries that
aren't being modified, then absolutely
continue to use the mechanisms that we
have in place today.
Now, I think it's the time to start
talking about the collectors. We've
talked about the source and how this
data gets published. A while ago, we
talked about you can send directly data
from a publisher to a back end, or you
can have a collector in between. What is
the collector? What does it do? Why
might I want one?
Yeah, so the collector is a separate
process that would be running inside
your environment. It is a binary that's
published as a separate binary or docker
image if you're if you're interested in
that. There's also uh packages for I
think Debian and and Red Hat.
And the collector is really a
destination for your telemetry that can
then act as a as a router. So it has,
you know, a
selection of I believe it's over 100
receivers which support different
formats and also can scrape data metric
data from different systems.
And it has exporters, and again, I lose
track of it, but I think it's over 100
formats of exporters that the open
telemetry collector supports.
So you can send data to it in one format
and export it using a different format
if you're if you're so keen on. You can
also use processors within the
collector, which allow you to manipulate
the data, whether it be for things like
redacting, you know, maybe PII that you
might have, or if you wanted to enrich
the data with some additional attributes
maybe about your environments that, you
know, only the collector would know
about.
And that's the collector in a nutshell.
It's, you know, available to deploy, as
I said, as a as an image as a package.
There's also, you know, you can deploy
using helm charts, you can deploy using
the open telemetry operator if you're
using a Kubernetes environment.
I'm going to delve in to some of those
internal components. I want to talk
first a little bit about the networking.
It can be simpler if I have n sources
and a number of k back ends instead of
an n cross k topology, an n cross one
and one cross k.
Do you have any thoughts on is that a
motivator to simplify your networking
and everything that goes along with
that? Is that a motivator for adopting a
collector?
Yeah, I think so. I think the collector
makes it very appealing for a variety of
reasons. One being that your egress from
your network may only be coming from one
one point. So from a, you know, security
auditing kind of perspective, you can
you can see where all the data is really
going out, rather than having a bunch of
different endpoints that have to be
connected to some external systems. So I
think from that point alone, it's it's
definitely worth deploying a collector
within a network.
I think
there is also the the ability to
throttle the the data that's going out
is is key. You know, if you have n
endpoints that are sending data, it's
really difficult to throttle how much
data is actually leaving your network,
which could, you know, end up being
costly. So if you wanted to, you know,
do things like sampling, you would
probably want to have a collector in in
place so that you could you could really
adjust it as needed.
How much telemetry can one instance of
collector handle?
Yeah, I mean, I think that
that always depends on the the size of
the instance that you're running. There
on the open telemetry collector
repository, there is a pretty
comprehensive benchmarks that have been
run against the collector for both for
for traces and logs and metrics. And I
believe the the instance sizes that were
used, I
if memory serves right, they were using
EC EC2 for the testing for the
benchmarks, and I believe that that's
all listed on the on the website there
for folks that are interested in finding
out.
If I wanted to either run more workload
than what I could put through one
instance, or for high availability
reasons have a clustered implementation
with multiple collectors, is it
possible, say, to put a load balancer in
front of it and distribute it? Or what
are the options for a a more clustered
implementation?
Yeah, so the the way you would want to
probably
deploy this is you would you would want
to use some kind of load balancer.
Depending on the the telemetry you're
sending out, you would you may want to
use like a routing processor that allows
you to to be more specific as to which
data each one of the collectors will be
receiving. So for example, if you had,
you know, maybe a bunch of collectors
that are deployed that are closer to
your applications, that would then be
routed through maybe a collector as a
gateway, and you wanted to send only,
you know, a certain number of traces to
the collector as a gateway, you could
fork it using using the routing
processor, you know, based on the trace
IDs or something like that if you wanted
to.
So with stateless servers, you can set
up a pretty dumb load balancer, and
every request would get routed
essentially to a random
instance. Is there any reason to have a
bit more of a sharding or
pinning of certain workloads in a
clustered implementation?
I think some of this depends on what
you're doing with the collectors. So for
example, if you're doing, you know,
sampling on traces, you wouldn't want
your sampling decision being made across
like there's there's no way to share
that sampling decision across
collectors.
And so you would want to be able to make
that decision on the same instance of
the collector, for example, and so you
would you would really want all of the
data for a specific trace to go to the
same collector to be able to make that
decision on the on the sample.
You used the word gateway, which is a a
common word, but I understand it means
something specific
in open telemetry, where you have a
gateway model and an agent model.
Explain the those two models, the
difference between them.
Yeah, so in in the agent deployment for
the open telemetry collector, you would
be running your open telemetry collector
on the same
the same host or the same node, you
know, maybe as part of a
demon set in Kubernetes. So you would
have a separate instance of the
collector for each one of the nodes that
are running inside your your
environment.
And you would have your application
sending data to the local agent before
it would then send it up to wherever
your destination is.
In the gateway deployment model, you
would have the collector act as a as a
standalone application, and, you know,
it would have its own deployment, you
know, maybe you would have one per per
data center or maybe one per region, and
that would act as maybe the egress out
of your out of your network. And that's
that's kind of the gateway deployment.
What you described as the agent model,
that sounds very similar to me of what
I've seen called sidecar with some other
services. Is agent the same as a
sidecar?
Yes and no, it can be like a sidecar.
You know, I think when I think of
sidecars, I would assume that they would
be attached to every application that's
running with a sidecar alongside it,
which would mean that you might end up
with, you know, several instances of the
collector running on the same
node, for example, which, you know, may
be necessary in specific cases, or it
may not be, really depends on your use
case, whether or not there's, you know,
accessibility from your application to
the host at all, that depends on what
your policies are how your policies are
confined or defined.
So it could be the same as a sidecar,
but it doesn't necessarily have to be.
Delving more into the internals of the
collector, what you can do,
you talked about processors and
exporters, and you've covered some of
this before, but why don't you start
with what are some of the major types of
of processors that you might want to
use? Yeah, so I think the two
recommended processors by the community
are the the batch processor, which, you
know, tries to take your data and batch
it rather than sending it every time
there's telemetry coming in.
This is trying to optimize some of the
compression and reduce the amount of
data that gets sent out.
So that's one of the recommended
processor. The other one is the the
memory limit processor, which limits
kind of the upper bound of memory that
you would allow a collector to use. So
you would probably want to use that, you
know, in the case of you have a specific
instance of some sort with some kind of
memory defined, you would want to
configure your memory limit processor to
be below that threshold so that when the
collector hits that memory limit, it can
start returning error messages to all of
its receivers so that, you know, maybe
the senders of the data can go ahead and
back off on the amount of data that's
being sent or something like that.
One of the other processors that's
really interesting to many folks is the
transform processor, which allow you to
use the OpenTelemetry transformation
language
to modify data. So, you know, maybe you
want to strip some particular attributes
or maybe you want to, you know, change
some values inside your telemetry data.
And you can do that with the transform
processor, which is still currently
under development, but I think it, you
know, early days in the processor, there
was a lot of a lot of excitement around
what could be done with processors, and
so people started developing filtering
processors and attribute processor for
metrics and all these other kind of
processors that
made it a little bit complicated to know
which processors folks should be using
because there's so many of them, and
sometimes, you know, one may support one
signal but not the other. Whereas, the
transform processor really tries to
maybe unify this into a single processor
so that that can be used to do all of
that. You said there's a lot of
excitement around this feature. What was
it that people found so exciting about
it?
Yeah, I think
from the maintainer and contributor
standpoint, I think we were looking
forward to deprecating some of the other
processors that, you know, could be
combined within a single one. It reduces
the Again, I I think it reduces the
cognitive load that people have to deal
with when, you know, ramping up on
OpenTelemetry. I think knowing that if
you want to modify your telemetry, all
you have to do is use this one processor
and, you know, learn the language that
you would need to transform the data as
opposed to going through and searching
the repository for, you know, five or
six different processors. I think that's
generally great to consolidate that a
lot of it. Tell me more about the
language that is used to do these
transforms.
Yeah, so the OpenTelemetry language for
folks that are interested in finding the
full definition is it's all available
inside the OpenTelemetry collector
contrib repository.
But it really allows folks to define in
a language that's signal agnostic what
they would like to do with their data.
So, it allows you to, you know, get
particular attributes, set particular
attributes, and modify data inside your
collector.
The other internal component of
collectors I want to spend some time on
is exporters.
What do those do?
Yeah, so the exporter take the data
that's been ingested by the
OpenTelemetry collector. So, the
OpenTelemetry collector uses receivers
to receive the data in a format that's
specific to whichever receiver is
configured. It then transforms the data
to internal data format within the
collector, and then it exports it using,
you know, whichever exporter is
configured. So, it the exporter's job is
to take the data, the internal data
format, and format it to the
specification of the destination of the
exporter.
Okay, so what are some examples of
different exporters that are available?
Yeah, so there's a bunch of exporters
that are vendor-specific exporters that
live in the repository today. There's
also many of the open source projects
have their own exporter. So, Jaeger has
its own, Prometheus has its own
exporter.
There's a few different logging options
as well. Yeah. So, data comes in, it
goes through some number of processors,
and then goes out through an exporter.
Is there a concept of a pipeline that
maps the path the data takes through the
collector?
Yeah, so the best place to find this is
really inside the collector
configuration. So, the collector is
configured using YAML, and at the very
essence of it, you would configure your
exporters, your receivers, and your
processors. And then you would define
the path through those components in the
pipeline section of the configuration,
which allows you to specify
what pipelines you want to configure for
tracing and for logs and for metrics
that to go through to the collector. So,
you would configure your receivers
there, and then your processors, and
then your exporters within each one of
those definitions. And you can configure
multiple pipelines for each signal,
giving them individual names. And how
does incoming data select or get mapped
onto a particular pipeline?
Yeah, so the way that the data would be
mapped on each pipeline is via the
specific receiver that is used to
receive the data. So, for example, if
you've configured, you know, a Jaeger
receiver on one pipeline and a Zipkin
exporter on a different pipeline, and
you're sending data through Zipkin, then
the pipeline that has the Zipkin
endpoint would be the destination of
that data, and then that's the pipeline
that the data would go through. So, does
each endpoint listen on a different
port, or does it have a path, or what's
the mapping?
Yeah, so that depends on the specific
receiver. So, some receivers have the
ability to configure different paths,
some only configure different ports. It
also depends on the protocol that you're
using for the receiver and whether it
supports it or not.
And as I mentioned, there's also these
things known as scrapers, which are
receivers that can go out and scrape
different endpoints for metrics, for
example. And those can also be
configured as receivers, which would
then take, you know, their own path to
the collector.
I think we've been mostly talking about
under the assumption of a push model,
but this The scraper sounds like it also
supports pull. Did I understand that
correctly? Yeah, that's correct. And,
you know, if you think of the Prometheus
receiver, for example, the Prometheus
receiver uses the pull model as well.
So, you would define, you know, the
targets that you would like to scrape,
and then the data would be pulled into
the collector as opposed to pushed to
the collector. So, to wrap this all up,
then I would instrument or configure my
sources to point them toward the OTel
collector or collectors in my network.
They would have a domain name or an IP
address and a port and maybe a path that
comes after that.
They're instrumented. They push data
out, it goes to the collector, the
collector will process it, and then
export it back into back end of choice.
Is that a good description of the whole
process? Yeah, that's exactly right. How
do the sources authenticate themselves
to the collector?
Yeah, so for authenticating to the
OpenTelemetry collector, there's several
extensions that are available for
authentication. So, there's OIDC
authentication extensions, there's the
bearer token authentication extension.
You can also use the basic auth
extension if you'd like.
So, there is a few different available
extensions for that.
Yeah, okay. Well, let's talk about
extensions. So, what are the extension
points that are offered?
Yeah, so extensions are essentially
components in the collector that don't
necessarily have anything to do with the
pipeline of the telemetry going through
the collector. And so,
some of the extensions that are
available are the pprof extension, which
allows you to get profiling data out of
the collector.
There's the health check extension,
which allows you to run health checks
against the collector.
And there's a few other ones that are
all available in the collector
repositories.
Okay. So, we've pretty much covered most
of what I had planned about what it
does, how it works. Suppose you have a
project that has not been built with
this in mind and is interested in
migrating. What is a possible migration
path to OTel from
uh project that might have been built
several years ago before this was
available? I would say the first path
that I would recommend to folks is
really to think about is there a way
that I can, you know, drop in a
collector and receive data in the format
that's already maybe being emitted by an
application. That's really the very
first step that I would I would suggest
taking.
You know, I know there is a few
different mechanisms for collecting
telemetry that predate the collector.
So, you know, Telegraf is an example of
one of those. If you have Telegraf
running in your environment and you're
interested in seeing if you can connect
it to the collector, maybe that's a good
place to start is, you know, to look at
connecting the two. And I know Telegraf,
for example, emits OTLP, so that's
already something that is somewhat
supported.
So, that's really the first step I would
take is, can I just get away with
dropping in a collector and emitting a
format that's maybe already supported?
One thing to note is, if you have a
format out there that's not currently
supported in the collector, you can
always go to the community and ask, hey,
is this a component that folks are
interested in in adopting? And that's
always a good avenue to kind of take on.
You know, if you've got commitment from
your organization to maybe change the
instrumentation libraries that you're
using within your code, then great. I
would, you know, start looking at
resources. I know there is a few
different use cases that have been
documented, I think, on opentelemetry.io
around migrating away from either
OpenTracing or OpenCensus.
So, I would definitely start looking for
those resources. So, we've talked about
the history and what it does. What's on
the road map?
Yeah, so on the road map for
OpenTelemetry, which we actually very
recently published. So, up until earlier
this year, there wasn't an official road
map published by the community, but
we're finally starting to change the
process a little bit to try and really
focus the efforts of the community.
So, currently on the road map, we have
five projects that are happening. So,
some of the work is being done around
both client-side instrumentation, so
either, you know, web browser-based or
mobile clients,
And around profiling, so this is
profiling data being emitted either
using an existing format that there's
some discussion around whether or not
there's going to be an additional signal
called profiles to open telemetry.
There's also a lot of effort being put
into trying to stabilize semantic
conventions.
So, you know, if you've seen the
semantic conventions inside the open
telemetry specification, you'll probably
know that a lot of them are marked as
experimental and that's just because we
haven't had the chance to really focus
the community on trying to come up to
agreement on what stable semantic
conventions should look like.
So, there's a lot of effort to bring in
experts in each one of the domains to
ensure that they make sense.
The other efforts that I'm excited about
because I'm part of the work is to put
together a configuration layer for open
telemetry as a whole so that users can
configure using, you know, some kind of
configuration file, take that
configuration file across any
implementation and know that the same
results will occur. So, for example, if
you're configuring your Jaeger exporter
in Python using this configuration
format, you'd be able to take that same
configuration to your .NET
implementation or Java and not have to
write code manually to translate that
configuration.
And then there's some effort around
function as a service support from open
telemetry. So, the group is currently
focused around lambdas because that's,
you know, the first serverless or
function as a service
model that's come to us.
But there's also effort to bring in, you
know, folks from Azure and and GCP as
well to kind of round that out. We're at
time. We've covered everything.
Where can listeners find your book?
Yeah, so you can find the book on it's
available on Amazon. You can also buy it
directly from Packt Publishing.
And yeah, it's also available at your
local bookstores.
If users would like to find your
presence anywhere on the internet, where
should they look?
Yeah, so they can they can find me on
LinkedIn, a little bit on Mastodon or on
Twitter, though not as much anymore.
And they can find me on the Slack
channels for the CNCF Slack instance.
I'm pretty active there.
Alex Boten, thank you very much for
speaking to Software Engineering Radio.
Yeah, thank you very much. It's been
great. This has been Robert Blumen for
Software Engineering Radio. Thank you
for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.